<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Parliament justified in their late proceedings against Charls Stuart, or a brief discourse concerning the nature and rise of government, together with the abuse of it in tyranny, and the peoples reserve. As also an answer to a certain paper, entituled, The humble advice of the lecturers of Banbury in the county of Oxon, and Brackley in the county of Northampton. / By J: Fidoe, T: Jeanes, W: Shaw, students in Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Fidoe, John, b. 1625 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E545_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863206</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91444)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E545[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Parliament justified in their late proceedings against Charls Stuart, or a brief discourse concerning the nature and rise of government, together with the abuse of it in tyranny, and the peoples reserve. As also an answer to a certain paper, entituled, The humble advice of the lecturers of Banbury in the county of Oxon, and Brackley in the county of Northampton. / By J: Fidoe, T: Jeanes, W: Shaw, students in Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Fidoe, John, b. 1625 or 6.</author>
                  <author>Jeanes, Thomas, d. 1668.</author>
                  <author>Shaw, William, student in Trinity College, Cambridge.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In part a reply to: The humble advice and earnest desires of certain well-affected ministers, lecturers of Banbury in the county of Oxon, and of Brackly in the county of Northampton, to his Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, General of the forces raised by the authority of Parliament; and to the General Councell of Warre.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humble advice and earnest desires of certain well-affected ministers, lecturers of Banbury in the county of Oxon, and of Brackly in the county of Northampton, to his Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, General of the forces raised by the authority of Parliament; and to the General Councell of Warre.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164954:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PARLIAMENT JUSTIFIED In their late Proceedings againſt Charls Stuart, Or a brief DISCOURSE concerning the Nature and Riſe of GOVERNMENT, Together with the Abuſe of it in Tyranny, and the PEOPLES Reſerve.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Sam. 17.28.</bibl> 
               <p>And Eliab ſaid, I know thy pride, and the haughtineſs of thy heart.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AS ALSO AN ANSWER To a certain PAPER, entituled, <hi>The humble Advice of the Lecturers of</hi> Banbury <hi>in the county of</hi> Oxon, <hi>and</hi> Brackley <hi>in the County of</hi> Northampton.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J: Fidoe, T: Jeanes, W: Shaw,</hi> Students in <hi>Trinity</hi>-Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:164954:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:164954:2"/>
            <head>Impartial READER,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et neither the Title nor the matter offend thee; the title is nothing elſe but the Books Name, by which you may diſtinguiſh it: Let not the Frontiſpiece af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright you, if ſo, rather throw it by: Christen it by what Name you will; Names or Titles are but tokens of things, and evidences of mens affections. We for our parts cannot (though others do) forfeit our Truſt to thoſe, who next unto our Creator, have been the Preſervers and Reſtorers of our Rights and Priviledges, which Tyranny had bereaved us almoſt of. We cannot ſuffer our ſelves to be called unthankful, or to be branded with Injuſtice; for if <hi>Cicero</hi> may be credited, there is Injuſtice in not turning away an injury, when it is in our power, as well as in doing it. Though we could humbly wiſh, That better wits, and riper judgements in theſe matters, would have undertaken this task; a task indeed able to break our ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, were there not <hi>Atlaſſes</hi> to bear us up, and who knows not but <hi>Atlas</hi> is able to bear up the whole world: <hi>The Tongue,</hi> ſaith St. James, <hi>is a little member, but ſet on fire of Hell, with it we bleſs God, and curſe man:</hi> Some men are of <hi>Jobs</hi> wife's temper onely in this different, ſhe adviſes her huſband to curſe God, they men, who ſees not innumerable <hi>Shimei's,</hi> that when <hi>Saul</hi> is departed, caſt reproaches upon our <hi>Davids</hi> or honorable worthies; how many <hi>Rabſhekahs</hi> that reproach, and with uncircumciſed tongues defie our <hi>Bethel,</hi> or Parliament, for God is wont to be in the Congregations of the Gods. We are true Engliſhmen, cannot endure to deny, but ingenuouſly to confeſs the leaſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors: Who knows not but that this Parliament and Army now on foot, have reſtored to us, not onely our well being, but our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lives (for not to ſpeak of the ſlavery of Subjects under Tyrants, who cannot call their lives their own, of which more ſhall be ſaid) from him that would have enſlaved us in more then Egyptian
<pb facs="tcp:164954:3"/>
bondage; for it is probable, that though <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Taskmaſters did afflict their bodies, yet their lives were not hazarded; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t who is ignorant of the purpoſe and intent of our adverſaries, not onely to have enſlaved our bodies, to have uſurped our poſſeſſions, but alſo our very lives, ſhould have been at ones will; who, we ſay, can be ſo unlike a man, as to labor to deſtroy thoſe that gave him life and all, that cannot be content not onely to receive good, but they muſt requite evil: <hi>O perverſe Generation, if you ſhould do good to thoſe that do good to you, what more do ye then the Heathens?</hi> But what example can you bring to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel this ingratitude? A few ſpare hours wrote this handful; we Schollars have not much time to ſpend upon the State, onely theſe few words may teſtifie our hearts, who are not onely willing to word it, but to juſtifie, if need be, ſome other way. We know we ſhall endanger the tongues of many a Zoïlus; what is it to us? Tongues are but childrens bables: Fools uſe their tongues, though not their Reaſon; To thoſe therefore that are ſo Eagle-eyed, that they can ſpy any fault but their own, we ſhall conclude with that of the Comedian, <hi>Ut Maledicere deſinant monemas maledicts ne noſcant ſua.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine as thou art for the Truth,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Fidoe,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Ieanes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VVilliam Shaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:164954:3"/>
            <head>THE PARLIAMENT JUSTIFIED In their late Proceedings againſt Charls Stuart.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore we proceed to Treat of Government in the riſe and growth, it will not be needleſs to give our definition of it, as we think fit enough to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing: We define it therefore a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſubmiſſion, when one or more rule, and others willingly obey (by which we diſtinguiſh it from Tyranny, of which more hereafter) for the end of all Government, it <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Populi,</hi> there being, as ſaith <hi>Cicero,</hi> a natural inſtinct in all Men and Beaſts to conſerve themſelves, and to ſhun thoſe things that are deſtructive: Now that this may be the eaſier done, Nature ſeeks Union; for all Union preſerves, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and disjunction kills: And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, that two are better then one, for if one fall, the other ſhall help him up: And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays in his Book <hi>De Repub.</hi> That man by nature is <hi>Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Animal:</hi> And therefore the ſame Author ſaith, That he that is a Member of no City, is either a notorious Rogue, or better then a Man: To which agrees <hi>Cains</hi> puniſhment, to be a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer and a vagabond, which he ſaid was to heavy for him to bear; and thoſe in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who wandred about in ſheep-skins and goat-skins, of whom the world was not worthy. The firſt age we confeſs dwelt apart, and lived <hi>vicati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is ſaid of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they lived like Beaſts in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164954:4"/>
holes, till by Government they were civilized: Now for the preſerving of mutual entercourſe between man and man; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who doth nothing in vain, endued man with a reaſonable Soul, and diſcurſive faculty or ſpeech, by which he might ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to his fellow Creatures, both joy and gladneſs, and alſo bewail his miſery: He hath made him alſo to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt good and evil, juſt and unjuſt, and that not upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, but by an innate Principle, by a Law written in his heart: But after that God had Created man a living ſoul, he forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that duty of his Creation, increaſed in wickedneſs; ſo that it was neceſſary for the conſervation of the whole, that this vaſt body might have ſome head to rule it, and ſomething that might be as a rule juſt and right to be governed by. Now this Government admits of ſeveral diviſions, and ſeveral names: For certain it is, that the firſt Image of Government that ever was, hath been betwixt Father and Family: For as much as thoſe things that are ſimple, are before <hi>Aggregates;</hi> and therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> firſt ſpeaks of a Houſe, as being the part of a City, and then of a City.</p>
            <p>A Houſe conſiſts of two parts, Servants, and Children; A Servant is nothing elſe but a living poſſeſſion, one who hath given up himſelf to the diſpoſing of another, and is as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the hand of his Maſter, who doth with him what he pleaſeth, ſave onely that which the Law of Nature, and the Law of the State wherein we live forbid. How this came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and whether God at firſt Created men alike, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men put themſelves firſt into this condition, we will not now diſpute; yet its probable by nature all men are alike free, and that either Tyranny made firſt ſlaves, or elſe happily ſome having ſpent their Talent, and being aſhamed to beg, put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into anothers poſſeſſion, though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, Some men are born to ſerve: Sure it is, that to command, and to be commanded, are not onely neceſſary, but alſo uſeful; for we ſee that in our ſelves, that conſiſt of ſoul and body; the ſoul commands, and the body as Servant obeys, yea, the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then had this notion; and that as ſome think, from the ſight of the goodly univerſe, or in imitation of the Celeſtial Deity: For ſeeing all things ſo fitly moved, they knew it could not be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164954:4"/>
but by ſome kinde of Government; whereupon ſome think there was a certain kinde of Government among the gods, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> being ſo often ſtiled King, but yet for the favorableneſs of his Scepter, ſtiled by <hi>Homer,</hi> the Father of gods and men. Now as we ſaid before, it is evident that the ſtate of a Servant is ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, becauſe that ſome that have been of Ingenuous Parents are compelled to it: And that which is natural to men; <hi>viz.</hi> Freedom, is ſo often fought for. Hence it is that we Read of the <hi>Servile Bellum,</hi> of the <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Romans.</hi> Now Servants are either ſuch as have voluntarily put themſelves on it, or elſe are ſuch by Law, by which it is eſtabliſhed that thoſe that are taken by War, are the ſpoils of the Conquerers; whence ſome are called <hi>Mancipia, Quaſi Manu Capta:</hi> And ſuch is the power of the Maſter over his ſervants, that the <hi>Scythians</hi> being gone over the Seas,<note place="margin">Iuſtin. Hiſt.</note> and their Servants Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling, they came to them with no other weapons but whips in their hands, a manifeſt token of their Servants ſubjection. The ſecond part of a houſe are children, the power of the father over them, is the ſame that a King hath over his people; and as a King is to provide for the good of his people, ſo the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his children, till they be able to provide for themſelves, which is the very inſtinct of Nature in all Creatures to provide for their yong, till they can pick their own meat. Such was the power of the father in <hi>Liberos,</hi> that the Romans had power over their childrens lives; examples hereof are exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many, and ſome think paralel'd in <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jephtha</hi>'s Vow: To put bounds to this power, it is not our intent, onely this we will ſay, which is granted by all (and which ſhews all power limited) that the Son is not to obey the Father in all things: The grounds of this is in the Jewiſh Law, and holds true by the Law of Nature; for if one ſhould be commanded by his Parents to ſacrifice to Idols, or the like, he is in no wiſe to obey him, it being contrary to an expreſs Command: Now though obedience is better then ſacrifice, yet it bindes not contrary to a Command; for in caſe the Magiſtrate ſhould command one thing, Parents another, we demand which is to be obeyed, ſince the Scripture is expreſs for both: There is reported in the <hi>Rabbines</hi> a pretty conceit;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164954:5"/>
A Boy was commanded by his Mother, to take a neſt of Birds with the Dam, the Law forbids it; the Boy aſſaying to break the Law in the obedience of his Parent, broke his neck; what a King is in his City, that a Father is in his Houſe: And as King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power is continued by the obedince of Subjects, ſo is an Houſe; <hi>For if a Houſe be divided againſt it ſelf, it cannot ſtand:</hi> And he that will learn to govern well, and be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber profitable to his City, muſt learn firſt to rule his own Houſe, which is a part of it. And now we come to Cities; The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral forms of Government, we ſhall onely name them; it being our intent onely to ſpeak of Government in its ſelf, not in this or that, which is onely accidental, and not eſſential; though ſome States ſtand beſt by one, ſome by another: The uſual forms are, firſt, Ariſtocratical, where men of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Parts and Truſt, are ſingled out for the good of others: Much like the States in <hi>Holland:</hi> and theſe gathered out of every county, and aſſembled together, ſeem to us to carry the true notion of a Parliament, the Commons being a repreſentative body. The ſecond is Democratical, when the people have a voyce in all that is done: Not much unlike this, was the <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus plebis</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who ſuffered the Senate to do nothing without Rogation of the people; and they had power to chooſe Conſuls, and to Enact Laws, which were therefore called, <hi>Plebiſcita.</hi> The third, is Monarchical, when one hath ſole command: concerning this, though it be very ancient, and the common opinion be, that in <hi>Nimrod</hi> or <hi>Belus,</hi> Father to <hi>Ninus,</hi> the firſt Monarchy began after the Flood; yet its probable there were Kings before him: For beſides that <hi>Cains</hi> building of a City, and denominating it from his Son <hi>Enoch,</hi> ſeems to have the Character of a Kingdom in it; yet ſome make <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt King, and that <hi>Seth</hi> ſucceeded in his Kingdom: And the Letter of <hi>Alexander</hi> to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in <hi>Joſeph-Ben-Gorion</hi> tells us, that <hi>Kenon</hi> the Son of <hi>Enoch,</hi> Grand-childe to <hi>Seth,</hi> was Emperor over the whole world, and buried in an Iſland of the <hi>Eaſt-Indian</hi> Sea; yea, ſome would have <hi>Monarchy</hi> derived from the very Law of Nature, and that Man as a Civil Creature was directed to this form, to which they bring that of <hi>Juſtin.</hi> In the beginning, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164954:5"/>
was with the Kings, whom no popular Ambition, but <hi>Spectata inter b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s moderatio</hi> exalted to it. And <hi>Homer</hi> ſaith, that one King is beſt; notwithſtanding, to ſpeak the truth, for all that can be ſaid of Monarchy, we think that no one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is more ſuitable to the nature of a man then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it being contrary to men to be in ſubjection, if they can avoid it; if any, that which is moſt conſervative, which would be diſputed: This onely we will ſay, That in the multitude of Counſellors, there is wiſdom. And the firſt diſorder of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in Scripture was in <hi>Saul,</hi> a King. The fourth form, concerning which we ſhall ſpeak a word, becauſe that now adays men argue from that to ours, is the Jewiſh policy, which <hi>Joſephus</hi> and all Writers confeſs to be a <hi>Theocratia,</hi> or a State mediately governed by God: For we put the caſe thus, and we ſay, That they could do nothing but by expreſs command from God, whether in Peace or War, (not to ſpeak of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> Typical of Gods preſence, who is both Light and Truth) they, we ſay, have their Government immediately from God: For its proper to Nations that are <hi>ſui Juris,</hi> to make War and Peace, as we ſee in the <hi>Romans,</hi> and all others: But the Jews could not make either War or Peace with any Nation, but by an immediate inquiry, which when they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, how often did it prove their deſtruction? And how often do we read in holy Writ, of asking counſel of God, and of doing nothing without him? Secondly, thoſe that had their Magiſtrates and their Laws from God, their Government is of God: But the Jews had their Magiſtrates, Judges, and Kings from God, yea their Laws, which are ſo often called The Book of the Law of the Lord. Now the Conſtitution of a Common-wealth being nothing but Heads, and Laws, it followeth, that they who had thoſe two from God, and could not Enact Laws, or Eſtabliſh Governors by a Power ſeated in themſelves, had the Fundamental Conſtitution of their Republique from God. Although it be otherwiſe in other Nations,<note place="margin">A digreſsion concerning the end of Magiſtracy.</note> in which we ſuppoſe the Power is fundamentally ſeated in the People (as will be ſaid) for whoſe good it was firſt inſtituted: For when <hi>Res Publica</hi> comes to be <hi>Res Privata,</hi> it ceaſes to be a Commonwealth, and is then Tyranny: The judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164954:6"/>
of the Iſraelites was to be without Magiſtrates, or elſe to have fooliſh Magiſtrates who knew no good but their own, whereas they ſhould be common Parents, conſulting not for themſelves but for their People, wherefore they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Shepherds: And thoſe that feed <hi>Iſrael</hi> in Scripture, are as well Magiſtrates, as Miniſters: <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Repub:</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places keeps this ſimilitude: A Shepherd, he ſaith, (ſpeaking of Governors) cares for nothing, but that he may keep what is committed to his care; the ſame ſaith, all Government (<hi>quatenus</hi> Government) commands us to take care for no other thing, but what is committed to our charge: And therefore <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſaith, That it behoveth a Prince firſt to govern himſelf, and then to govern his Subjects; for he that knows no order, cannot order others; the ſame would have them to conſider, that they themſelves are ſubject to Command: Not like the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who made all Slaves but his Wife, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law is to be his rule, the King of men and gods, ſaith <hi>Pindar:</hi> Not ſo much that written in Books or Tables, but <hi>viva in corderatio,</hi> always dwelling, always watching with him; and therefore the King was to have the Law continually read to him: And it may be the cauſe why ſo much ſin in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was, becauſe the Law was loſt and not found, or at leaſt not uſed till <hi>Joſiah,</hi> at which time there was great joy for the finding of it, and the King read in it from Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing until Evening: Not much unlike this is that of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> King, who had one to come to him every Morning with theſe words, <hi>Riſe O King, Care for thoſe things which</hi> Oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſdes <hi>would have you care for:</hi> They are called Miniſters of God (yea gods) to preſerve mens Eſtate, and what nature hath beſtowed upon them, to diſtribute it and preſerve it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at firſt, the <hi>Romans</hi> had onely their Senatus which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of old men, beſt able to judge of things, being experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in the affairs of this world: Concerning this, <hi>Plutarch</hi> hath wrote a Book, in which is elegantly diſcuſſed who are fitter for the Commonwealth, youths, or old men; for we know that <hi>Rehoboams</hi> yong men made the Tribes fall off: The yoke of Tyranny being inſufferable, and therefore upon due conſideration and power to be caſt off; for who is ignorant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164954:6"/>
that the firſt Power entruſted was but ſmall, and no more, then if a blinde man ſhould entruſt a ſeeing friend with his leading, and he contrary to his Truſt, ſhould either attempt a murther, or elſe a throw from ſome <hi>preoipice:</hi> we ſay, that if this man ſhould receive his ſight; he may then caſt him off, for that he deſired him to lead him, not to throw him down. Now having ſaid ſomething of Government in general, as alſo of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of it, we ſhall proceed to that which indeed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the abuſe of it, and that is Tyranny, or an unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and uſurped Power, by which one man, or more, without an Appeal to the Law of Nature, written in the heart of every man, or to that Divine written Law of God, entrench upon (by freely exerciſing) the Natural or Political Rights of others, according to their own pleaſure: It is a Power meerly Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, which is ſo far from coming under the notion of <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> as it is altogether Repugnant to the Law of Reaſon and Nature; neither of them allowing the private Intereſt of a part, to exalt it ſelf above the common good of the whole; whence comes the ruine of a body Natural? but from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabounding, unlimited and Tyrannical Power, of ſome one of the Malignant humors: As <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength lay in his Locks, ſo that of a State lies in the Complication of an univerſal Intereſt, common unto all; we ſhall ſpeak of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny under a twofold account: 1. There may be Tyranny by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, as thoſe that know any thing in Hiſtory, know that the foundation upon which the firſt four Monarchies was built, was an uſurped Power, got by the Sword: For indeed, the world being enlarged, and the eſtate of the people confuſed, it was then a fit time for Tyranny to take its original; every one being a Law to himſelf, and Interpreter of his own Actions, no marvel that the ſtrongeſt governed all the reſt at his own will: If this principle of Tyranny be good, other men may not onely free themſelves from ſlavery as ſoon as they can, but alſo exerciſe power (when its put into their hands) againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, their former oppreſſors; it will amount but to <hi>Lex tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> to pay them home in their own Coyn, from their own Principles. 2. Tyranny may be by Male-Adminiſtration, or by abuſing and going beyond the Truſt repoſed in a man, by a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164954:7"/>
Kingdom or State: The preſent age in which we live, preſents before our eyes an example moſt freſh and lively; That our late King, <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> was not a Tyrant in the firſt ſence, is confeſſed by all, witneſs his Oath at his Coronation, as alſo his claiming Intereſt in the Crown, by a lineal deſcent from <hi>William</hi> the Conquerer, who thought the choice or Election of the People, a better and ſurer Title then Conqueſt: But to free him from Tyranny in the latter ſence, who can? unleſs ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits wilfully prejudiced againſt the Honorable Parliament, and the High and Supreme Court of Juſtice; for that he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the People with his power, is clear, it being irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to think that our Anceſtors gave any ſuch abſolute unlimitted Power unto our late Kings Predeceſſors, as that they might uſe them how they pleaſed; and notwithſtanding, that no reſerve left in people, when as the exerciſe of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the beſtowing it upon one or many, is founded in the conſent and mutual agreement of the whole body, or ſociety of men in a State-Government or Magiſtracy, is indeed a power ordained of God, and upon no pretence to be reſiſted: but when a man through depraved Principles of Tyranny and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, uſurps over the Conſcience in things Spiritual and Divine, above the reach or determination of the Spirit of a man, by propoſing his will and fancy to them for a Law, or when he entrenches upon Natural or Civil Right, then he loſeth the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Magiſtrate, becauſe he goes contrary to the end of the Government of that Fundamental Law, which is <hi>Salus Populi:</hi> But ſuppoſe our Forefathers had given away to any one man without a remedy or appeal, that power originally in them by way of diſpenſation, it will not follow, ſeeing nature makes us free, and this freedom never given away by us, we ſhould be bound to embrace any ſlavery our Forefathers ſhould ſeemingly caſt us in, they could only engage for themſelvs, they had nothing to do with their Poſterity, as to take from us what Nature gives: Now that <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> broke this Truſt, which we have ſhewed he muſt neceſſarily be intruſted with, we ſhall not need to ſpend time in the probation of, it being abundantly proved by many learned Pens, we ſhall proceed to ſhew the lawfulneſs, for Free-born men in a State, according to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164954:7"/>
that Fundamental Law of Reaſon, to execute Juſtice upon a man degenerated into Tyranny: In doing this, we ſhall not ſpend time to Treat of the ſeveral names and kindes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, we having ſpoken ſomewhat of them before, yet this we would put you in minde of, That <hi>Theocracy</hi> was onely of Divine inſtitution, and that this was onely proper to the Jews: As for the reſt, they are of humane inſtitution, and are derived from the People; and the people have power to put down, or to alter theſe or any of theſe as they finde occaſion; ſeeing it is confeſſed by all, that <hi>Salus Populi eſt Suprema Lex,</hi> All Governors are but Truſtees unto the People: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the people finde them acting contrary to the Truſt repoſed in them, they may juſtly take it from them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to others; or in caſe they cannot finde others that they can entruſt, or in caſe they finde that Government inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the State, they may alter it, and keep the Truſt in their own hands: But we know that there are many, who deny the Supreme Power to be in the people; and thoſe men make it Haereditary to Kings and their Succeſſors, and that by vertue of the Laws of this Nation. But concerning the firſt, we would have them ſee from whence this Succeſſion did proceed; There could not be a Succeſſion before there was an Election; and if ſo, then either the firſt King muſt have this power in himſelf, or receive it from the people: Now we ſuppoſe that no men are ſo abſurd, as to affirm it was in the firſt King, before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Crown and Power from the people; and if ſo, then the prime and chief Power muſt neceſſarily be in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: If Kings obtain Crowns and Kingdoms any other way, it muſt be by Conqueſt; and if that be a ſufficient Title, then if the great Turk ſhould invade our Kingdom, we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily own him as our lawful Soveraign; and if any private man by force can beat another out of his poſſeſſion, he may lawfully enjoy it, and he to whom it did of right belong, muſt acquieſce, and not ſeek to regain it. But there are ſome that ſay it is not our caſe for we have had a Succeſſion of kings ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of this Nation, for divers Generations: But we deſire to know of them, by whom thoſe Laws were En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted; as alſo, who the firſt king was, from whence this Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164954:8"/>
did proceed: And as for this firſt king, which was the main Baſis or ſtock from whence this Succeſſion took its riſe, It was <hi>William,</hi> ſirnamed Baſtard, Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> who invaded this Land, and deſtroyed many of the Free-born Engliſh: We ſhall not ſpend time to diſpute what Title he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he had to the Crown: But this onely we ſhall ſay, If he had any Intereſt, it could be but a weak one, ſeeing he was an illegitimate: We ſhall rather ſpeak of the Arbitrary and Tyrannical Government he exerciſed on the Free-born Engliſh, as ſoon as he had invaded this Nation, and obtained the Crown: How he ſubverted their Laws, and by force En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted and put in Execution ſuch as were moſt ſuitable to his own Tyrannical Spirit, to the great diſlike and male-content of the people; Though they were conſtrained to ſubmit unto them, as appears by the ſeveral inſurrections of the Engliſh, both of the Nobility and Commonalty, who ſeveral times endeavored to throw his ſervile yoke off their ſhoulders: Amongſt whom <hi>Edgar Ethling</hi> was chief leader, who alſo is reported to have had the greateſt intereſt in the Crown, with whom joyned <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Morcar,</hi> who were brethren of the Queen.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not ſtand to tell you of the multitudes ſlain in divers places, nor of his unjuſt acting in particulars; Though Hiſtory makes it plainly appear, That in a Bloody and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous maner, he diſmembred many, put out the eyes of ſome, and ſlow many hundreds which were at his mercy: Onely this we will ſay of him in general, He came in a Conquerer, and lived a Tyrant; but it was not our intent to have ſpoken any thing concerning him, onely this we thought good briefly to diſcover, the ſtock from whence this Regal Succeſſion did ſpring. We ſhall not ſpeak any thing of the Tyranny of his Succeſſors, nor how far they walked in his wicked ſteps, but ſhall paſs all over in ſilence, until the unhappy Reign of <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> who came unto the Crown after the death of king <hi>James</hi> his Father, his Brother <hi>Henry</hi> being before poyſoned: We ſhall not here ſtand to reckon up the Capital crimes which were committed by him in the beginning and middle of his Raign; neither ſhall we undertake to determine how far he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164954:8"/>
countenanced the Spaniſh Faction; neither ſhall we intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the tranſactions of <hi>Ree, Rochel,</hi> &amp;c. But we ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſcend to the laſt ſeven years of his Raign, and here we could declare ſufficiently the horrid impieties and bloody ſlaughters committed by him: But ſeeing the illegality of his proceedings is ſufficiently proved, and ſo fully made manifeſt to all the world, we ſhall not ſpend time to diſpute of it, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all men, unleſs wilfully blinde, may read it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n bloody Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters; but we ſhall rather ſpeak ſomething concerning the juſtneſs of the Parliaments proceedings againſt him: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apparent he degenerated from a king unto a Tyrant, it was not unjuſt for them to Act againſt him, as a Tyrant; now all rational men acknowledge it a juſt act to execute a Tyrant: But the difference amongſt them is, By whom he ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted? Whether by a Native? or Stranger? or for any man without Judgement? or elſe whether it muſt be done by ſome Court of Judicature? and to this laſt moſt men agree: We read of <hi>Nero</hi> &amp; <hi>Maximinus,</hi> how they were both executed by the power and command of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate: And likewiſe divers of the kings of <hi>Denmark,</hi> for Tyranny have been Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, Impriſoned and Executed; ſo odious is Tyranny to all men, that the very Heathens, when <hi>Hercules</hi> had ſubdued Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, they numbred him among the gods: And in our Neighbor Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Lord Preſident of the High Court of Judicature, hath given a very large example, and therefore we ſhall paſs that by.</p>
            <p>But if we had had no preſident, either Domeſtick or Forraign, yet the very Law of Reaſon and Nature, were ſufficient to clear them in it: As for the Laws of the Land, they are all ſubordinate unto this of Reaſon, and muſt give place to it: And ſeeing kings have always had a Negative Voyce, which they have kept up by uſurpation, it is not to be expected the letter of the Law ſhould ſo fully ſpeak to their particulars: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot but acknowledge, that we are abundantly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, in the juſtneſs of their proceedings in the Tryal, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and Execution of <hi>Charls Stuart.</hi> Now ſeeing Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is ſo neceſſary (as we have already declared) and Tyranny taken away by Gods bleſſing, and the endeavors of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:164954:9"/>
our Honorable Parliament, and Renowned Army: Our earneſt deſire is, That God would direct and enable them to ſettle a Government, that all men, eſpecially thoſe that are in places of Truſt, as well in Univerſities as elſewhere, may be compelled to acknowledge the Supreme Power of Parliament, which they have received, and are entruſted with by the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that we may have cauſe to rejoyce in them, and to bleſs God for them, and as long as they ſhall thus Act according to their Truſt, we ſhall not ceaſe to be their faithful and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Servants, to the utmoſt of our powers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:164954:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ANSWER TO A BOOK ENTITULED,</hi> The humble Advice of certain Preachers of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> in the county of <hi>Oxon,</hi> and <hi>Brackley</hi> in Northamptonſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E had thought, that ſuch had been the Equity of our Parliaments proceedings, and ſo manifeſt to all the ſeeing world, that even Envy her ſelf would have been ſilenced; but we had delivered to us a Paper, Entituled as is mentioned; which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, though it came to our hands like an old Almanack, bearing date from before the death of him, whom you ſtiled, <hi>Your Dread Soveraign,</hi> yet we could not paſs it over, without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you how far you have out ſtript-your Claſſical bounds. As for the particulars in the Book, having peruſed it, we finde neither good Reaſon, nor good Arguing; yet nevertheleſs, we will ſingle out two or three, to which we will briefly Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Whereas you inſtance in the prophanation of your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Oathes, we Demand,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How far Oathes and Covenants are obligatory?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ask, what you meant by entring into Oathes and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:164954:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:164954:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:164954:11"/>
Covenants, of Reſtoring <hi>Charls Stauart,</hi> and Reforming Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? As to the firſt, we ſay, That ſome Oathes and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants are not to be made, and if inconſideratey made, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratey broken; for we know, that more then forty of the Jews bound themſelves by Oath, <hi>Not to eat nor drink till they had killed Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the ſecond we make ſome Quaeres:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether the Covenant to reſtore the King, was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any condition? If ſo, it was unlawful; for to inſtance in a Simile, Suppoſe a man ſhould ingage himſelf to another, to defend and protect him from all violence; put caſe that perſon violate the Laws of the Land, and is therefore condemned to dye, that mans Oath bindes him not (yea cannot) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him.</item>
               <item>2. If your Covenant had a condition, whether to reſtore the King to his Throne, without reference to the peoples Liberty; if ſo, its all one, as if you ſhould engage your ſelves in ſlavery, and your actions differed nothing from the Cavaliers, whoſe ultimate end it was, to reſtore the King unto his Throne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſatisfaction.</item>
               <item>3. What you meant by the Reformation according to the Word of God? whether the impoſal of an outward Form, to which all men ſhould be forced to give an aſſent? if ſo, you drive at nothing elſe but the Popiſh and Prelatical Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</item>
               <item>4. Whether all have equal light, or ſee with the ſame eyes? if not, while ſhould any be compelled outwardly to profeſs that, which inwardly they never knew?</item>
               <item>5. Whether the Reformation of Religion be not rather Internal and Spiritual, then the impoſing of any External Form of Government?</item>
               <item>6. Whether Chriſt is not the alone King of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael? if ſo, then the Reformation is wholly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by his Spirit.</item>
               <item>7 Whether the Magiſtrate, as a Subordinate Reformer, hath any thing to do with the Church, but to preſerve them from injuries as men.</item>
               <item>8. What is the Toleration which you ſay is no way conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:164954:11"/>
to the Word of God? if Chriſtian liberty, we diſſent.</item>
               <item>9. We demand, whether you hold perfection in this life? if ſo, why ſpeak you and write contrary to your principles? if not, why account you all erroneous that diſſent from you?</item>
               <item>10. Whether the Reſults of any Aſſembly, in matters of Faith and Conſcience, are obligatory? if ſo, they muſt be infallible, and then we demand whence they had their infallibility.</item>
               <item>11. Whether the interpretations of Scripture, made by any Aſſembly, hath as much <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> as the Scripture it ſelf?</item>
            </list>
            <p>To all which Quaeres we ſhould gladly receive particular ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>We likewiſe finde you in your Paper, urging Statute Law; we thought you had been Diſpencers of the Goſpel, and not Expounders of the Law; Lecturers, not Barriſters; Countrey Miniſters, not Inns of Court Gentlemen: You ſay, you are informed by Law, that the King could do no wrong; ſurely it was out of ſome of Judge <hi>Ienkins</hi> his Papers; as for your reading it in Parliament Declarations, we conceive it was in <hi>Mecurius Aulicus,</hi> whom you took for the <hi>Moderate Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencer.</hi> We likewiſe finde you too much intrenching upon the Authority of the Magiſtrates, adviſing his Excellency not to meddle, without direction from the Aſſembly. Unleſs we are miſtaken, this borders upon Popery, which commands no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be done in State, without the Aſſent of Eccleſiaſtique perſons. For your better ſatisfaction, we will give you the Popes own words, as we finde them in a Bull written to <hi>Philip</hi> the fair King of <hi>France,</hi> mentioned in the French Hiſtory; the words are theſe, <hi>Boniface Biſhop, Servant of the Servants of God, to</hi> Philip <hi>King of Frenchmen, Fear God, obſerve his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; we will thee to underſtand, That thou art ſubject to us both in Spiritual and Temporal things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We likewiſe finde you ſtiling your ſelves Watchmen and Seers: If Watchmen, we adviſe you to have a care that you give us no more falſe Alarums, for fear of Martial Law; and as you are Seers, we deſire you to keep in minde, That the Seers of Iſrael have oftentimes been blinde.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
